so we have seen that we want the cash to
be small and fast but not too small
because then it keeps very little stuff
so that it has very few hits so what are
the cache sizes that we have actually
observed in real processors there is a
complication there in that modern
processors usually have several caches
not just one so depending on which cash
are we talking about it might be larger
or smaller
so let's look at caches that we call l1
or level 1 caches which are the caches
that directly serve is the read and
write requests from the processor so
when the processor wants to read a write
it first goes to the l1 cache to check
if it has a hit if the l1 cache has a
mess then things get complicated because
before we go to the main memory we go to
other caches and in several lessons we
will actually see how that works but for
now let you see how big are these level
1 caches in recent processors typical
sizes of the l1 cache have been 16 to 64
kilobytes this is large enough to get
about 90% hit rate meaning only 1/10 of
all the accesses from the processor end
up going beyond this cache yet these are
still small enough to have the hit time
that is equal to 1 2 3 processor cycles
so we spend very few processor cycles
waiting for the data to come back from
this cache if it's a hit
recall that memories have hundreds of
cycles so this is very very fast
compared to the memory